Ougi Oshino's true identity
is Koyomi Araragi.
忍野扇の正体は阿良々木暦だ
Ougi Oshino is an apparition
created by Koyomi Araragi.
忍野扇は
阿良々木暦が生み出した怪異だ
Just as my older sister, Tooe Gaen,
created an apparition called the Rainy Devil.
私の姉 臥煙遠江が
レイニー・デヴィルなる怪異を作り上げたようにね
The unknown apparition created by Tooe Gaen
was the materialization of her self-control.
臥煙遠江の作り上げた正体不明の怪異は
彼女の自制心が形になったものだった
Taking that quasi-darkness,
その "くらやみ" もどきを 西洋の怪異
and arranging it into the form of
the western apparition called Rainy Devil,
"レイニー・デヴィル" という形に整理することで
she settled the score.
決着をつけた
You could say that Ougi Oshino
言うなら忍野扇は
is your own desire to criticize yourself.
阿良々木暦の自己批判精神だ
Of course, that's not all she is.
もちろん 彼女はきみの自己批判精神だけで
出来上がっているわけじゃあない
It was last August.
昨年八月のことだ
The case where Hachikuji-chan
was assaulted by the "darkness".
八九寺ちゃんが "くらやみ" に襲われた事件
The first phase was that Koyomin, through
the incident, learned about the "darkness".
こよみんがそれで "くらやみ" を知ってしまったことが第一フェイズ
You learned of a phenomenon
that corrects mistakes.
"間違いを修正する" 現象を
It tells you that what's
forbidden is forbidden.
駄目なものは駄目
What is wrong is wrong.
間違っているものは間違っている
It judges things.
そう裁いてくれる存在を知ってしまった
Now, the second phase was the confrontation
with the first Apparition Killer.
さて 第二フェイズは初代怪異殺しとの対決だ
During the first encounter,
初回遭遇時に 駿河が
Suruga's Rainy Devil left arm had been hit
by the Energy Drain from the first one, yes?
"レイニー・デヴィル" の左腕を 初代の彼に
エナジードレインされているだろう?
Here, the undiluted essence of the
"unknown" my older sister created
ここで 私の姉が作った "正体不明" の原液が
combined with the original.
初代の彼に混ざってしまった
Through Shinobu Oshino,
you and he understand one another.
忍野忍を通じて 彼ときみは
通じ合っている
In fact, Shinobu-chan
had eaten the first one.
どころか 忍ちゃんが初代の彼を "食べて" しまっているからね
Thanks to that food chain,
a part of my older sister's legacy
食物連鎖で私の姉の遺産の一部が
flowed into you through Shinobu-chan.
忍ちゃんを通して
きみの中に流れ込んでしまった
And the result was the birth
of an "unknown" equipped with
結果 この町で起きた怪異現象及び
それにまつわるエピソードを備えた
all of the apparitions in this town, and
everything that had happened with them.
"正体不明" が 生まれるに至った
Because of its nature and how it was created,
Ougi Oshino is able to
wield Heart-under-blade's
physical materialization skill,
at the very least.
By the way, concerning the surname "Oshino,"
it originates from Shinobu Oshino.
ところで 忍野という苗字については
忍野忍に由来するものなんだよ
The fact that I foolishly called
myself that guy's little sister
私が迂闊にも
八月に奴の妹を名乗ってしまったのが
turned out to set a bad precedent.
悪い先例になったのだろう
However, Koyomin's singularity
was that the apparition
しかし こよみんが特異だったのは
作り出した怪異が
he created was an apparition
that attacked himself.
己自身を攻撃する怪異だったということだ
You have, from spring break,
somewhere in your heart,
きみは 春休みからこっち
どこか心中に
had awareness that you are
cheating all over your body.
身体中に
ズルをしているという自覚があった
You helped Kiss-shot Acerola-orion
Heart-under-blade out of sympathy...
キスショット・アセロラオリオン・ハートアンダーブレードを
同情心で助けてしまった
and you wanted to face the consequences.
その報いを受けたかった
You grew a friendship
with Tsubasa Hanekawa...
羽川翼と友情を築いた
but you kept worrying if you were worthy,
since you couldn't live up to her feelings.
だけど彼女の気持ちに応えられなかった自分にその資格があるのか
ずっと悩んでいた
You helped Hitagi Senjyogahara
with her long-term worries...
戦場ヶ原ひたぎを長年の悩みから救った
but you kept thinking how you ended up dating
her as "taking advantage of her weakness."
その後彼女と付き合うことになったのを
どうしても "弱味に付け込んだ" んじゃないかと考えてしまう
You respect Suruga Kanbaru...
神原駿河を尊敬する
but you felt inferiority because you couldn't
live in her straightforward manner.
あんな真っ直ぐな生きかたができないことが
コンプレックスだ
You helped Nadeko Sengoku...
千石撫子を助けたけれど
...but back then, the person you really
wanted to help wasn't just Nadeko Sengoku.
あのとき本当に助けたかったのは
千石撫子だけじゃあなかった
You gradually reconciled
with Shinobu Oshino...
忍野忍となし崩し的に和解してしまったけれど
but was that even allowed?
それは許されることなんだろうか?
In the first place, isn't it unfair
to freely use powers of immortality?
そもそも不死身の力を自由に使い熟すって
卑怯じゃないのか?
Shouldn't there be
consequences to face for it?
報いがあるべきなんじゃないのか?
Aren't I...
僕は
the worst kind of human imaginable?
人として最低じゃないのか?
The portion of your mind
that criticizes itself
そういった 自身に対する批判精神が
あますところなく発露した姿が忍野扇であり
manifested itself entirely
in the form of Ougi Oshino.
The girl you could call Dark Koyomin.
ダークこよみんとも言うべき彼女であり
That is why, like the darkness,
she took things one by one,
だから彼女は "くらやみ" のごとくひとつひとつ
with the case of Sodachi Oikura as
a springboard, and crushed them.
老倉育の件をたたき台にして
ある意味地道に 潰して行った
Meme Oshino and Yoduru Kagenui...
忍野メメと影縫余弦
That, and probably Deishu Kaiki after he
finished the case concerning Nadeko Sengoku.
それにたぶん
千石撫子の件を片付け終えたあとの貝木泥舟もだな
Rest assured, Koyomin.
安心したまえ こよみん
If you exterminate Ougi Oshino,
you'll probably find them easily.
忍野扇を退治すれば
普通に発見できるだろうさ
She still has things that are left undone.
彼女にはまだ
やり残していることがある
Right. Tsukihi Araragi, your little sister.
そう 阿良々木月火
きみの妹
The immortal apparition, the Shideno-bird.
不死身の怪異
しでの鳥
There's no chance whatsoever that
part of you isn't concerned with whether
人間に擬態したまま生き延びている彼女を
本当にこのままにしていていいのかという気持ちが
it's okay for her to live
while pretending to be a human being.
きみの中にないわけがない
That's why I used her as a lure.
だからここで
私はきみの妹を囮(おとり)に使う
Yup, that's right. I have no evidence.
そうだ 証拠はない
Everything I said just
now is only speculation.
今言ったことは
すべて推測に過ぎない
But you understand it, don't you?
だけどわかっているはずだろう?
You know better than anyone else
きみが誰より知っている
the true identity of Ougi Oshino.
忍野扇の正体を
That is why it must be you who
discloses her true identity.
だからこそ彼女の正体を暴くのは
きみでなければならないんだ
Go be victorious in the
battle against yourself.
自分との闘いに勝利したまえ
It's rather simple, isn't it?
簡単なことだろう?
他人のために自分を殺す
きみが毎日やっていることだ
Killing yourself for the sake of others.
It's something you do every day.
It's Koyomi Araragi, the one
that you loathe the most.
きみがもっとも憎む 阿良々木暦だ
So... go end it all.
だから 終わらせなさい
By your hands, you need to end it all.
きみの手で
きみが終わらせなさい
That is the end... of your adolescence.
それがきみの 青春の終わりだ
Ougi Dark
Part Three
Your true identity... is me.
きみの正体は 僕だ
You are me.
きみは 僕だ
Ougi Oshino... is Koyomi Araragi.
忍野扇は 阿良々木暦だ
Wow, that was rather quick.
The main act has already arrived?
あー 随分と早いですねえ
もう真打のご登場ですか
Is it because of the severity of the
lies I told, the sins I have committed?
ついた嘘の
犯した罪の大きさゆえですか?
To think I was trying to act
the part of such a thing...
こんなものを演じようとしていたなんて
I have to say, I must
have been rather insane.
我ながらどうかしていたとしか思えませんねえ
Didn't you know that this
was going to happen?
きみにはこうなることがわかっていたんじゃないのか?
If you really are me,
きみが僕だと言うのなら
the fact that I'd be waiting here,
僕がここで待っていることも
the fact that I'd already
learned who you really are...
僕がもう
きみの正体を見抜いていたことも
If you knew, then why come?
なのにどうして
ここに来たんだ?
There are times where you have to fight,
even if you know you're going to lose.
負け戦でも
戦わなくちゃいけないときはあるんですよ
If I could say something akin to dying words,
あえて遺言めいたものを言わせてもらえるならば
I believe that, in my own way,
私は私なりに
I was able to make Koyomi Araragi's
adolescence into something more right,
阿良々木暦の青春を
よりよくはできなくとも
even if I couldn't make it better.
より正しくはできたのではないでしょうか
If you're saying that this is right...
これが正しいって言うんだったら...
Then I don't need what's right.
僕は正しさなんていらないんだよ
Do you know how many problems you've
caused, for how many people?
いったい どれだけの人に迷惑をかけたと思ってるんだ
If you're saying someone was harmed,
then I'll say that they deserved it.
もしも被害を受けたのだとしたら
それは報いと言うべきですよ
It is not that I personally
have done anything.
私が何をしたというわけでもありません
In reality, you fully understand
that as well, don't you?
本当はあなただってわかっているでしょう?
That trouble, harm, misfortune...
They aren't things that are cut-and-dry.
迷惑も 被害も 不幸も
そう簡単に 割り切れるものじゃないんだって
So the right thing is cut-and-dry?
正しさなら 割り切れるのかい?
What is right, and what is wrong...
Can you cut them apart?
何が正しくて何が間違っているかを
きみなら切り分けられるのかい?
Even if you can't decide what's right,
何が正しいかは決められなくとも
you can decide which side
is right, can't you?
どっちが正しいかは決められるでしょう?
In Sodachi Oikura's case, I was wrong.
老倉育の件では 私が間違ってました
In Nadeko Sengoku's case, I was right.
千石撫子の件では 私が正しかった
In Tadatsuru Teori's case...
I guess we call that a draw.
手折正弦の件は 痛み分けですかね
I had thought that I could win
that in a one-on-one fight.
単体の勝負としては勝てると思っていたんですけれどね
Challenge
So after all this, Ougi-chan...
Me or you—who was right?
結局のところ扇ちゃん
僕ときみのどちらが正しかったんだ?
As I am the one disappearing like this,
it means that Araragi-senpai, you were right.
こうして私が消滅するんだから
阿良々木先輩 あなたのほうが正しかったということでしょう
Congratulations, Araragi-senpai.
おめでとうございます 阿良々木先輩
Everything you have done until
now has not been wrong.
これまであなたがしてきたことは
間違いじゃあなかった
It was right.
正しかった
This is the end of adolescence.
青春の終わり ですね
Or perhaps the end of a story?
あるいは物語の終わり ですか
Oh, this is nothing significant at all.
何 こんなことは大したことではありません
It's not the end of one's life, and it's
far from enough to be the world's end.
人生の終わりってわけじゃないし
世界の終わりにも全然足りない
It's just the end of one
of your many stories.
あなたの物語の
数あるひとつが終わるだけです
It's not even the final episode or anything.
最終回でもなんでもない
I'm glad that I could disappear
like this before you graduated.
こうして あなたが卒業する前に
消滅できてよかった
Thank you for all your hard work.
お疲れ様でした
Farewell, Araragi-senpai.
さようなら 阿良々木先輩
Farewell, Ougi-chan.
さようなら 扇ちゃん
Farewell, Ougi Oshino.
さようなら 忍野扇
Farewell, my adolescence.
さようなら 僕の青春
Never mind! I just can't do it!
って やっぱり無理
A-Araragi-senpai? Wh-What are...
あ... 阿良々木先輩!?
な 何を...
What are you... thinking?
何を考えているんですか あなたは!
You're not immortal, but you're
trying to save someone else.
不死身でもない癖に
他人を助けようとするなんて
I-In the end, that's how you are?
け... 結局 あなたはそうなんですか
Do you throw your life away so
easily for the sake of others?
他人のために
簡単に命を投げ出してしまうんですか
So you are going to save
even someone like me,
あなたを批判するだけだった
who did nothing but criticize
you and make you suffer?
あなたを責めたてるだけだった
私みたいな奴まで助けちゃうんですか
What good does it do if you die?
死んでどうなるんですか
What's the point of saving me here?
ここで私を助けることにどんな意味があるんです
You're wrong after all.
やっぱり あなたは間違っている
You are wrong as a person.
あなたは 人として間違っている
You are the absolute worst as a person.
あなたは人として最低だ
I didn't... save someone else.
他人を... 助けたんじゃない
Right now... I just saved myself.
僕は今 自分を助けたんだ
Hitagi did. Hanekawa did. Shinobu did.
Ononoki-chan did. Everyone saved me.
ひたぎ... が 羽川が... 忍が... 斧乃木ちゃんが...
みんなが 助けてくれた
If everyone had saved me,
and I didn't save myself?
みんなが助けてくれた僕を
僕が助けないなんて
I just can't allow such a thing to happen!
そんなこと
あっていいわけないだろう
Oh, brother.
I had planned for a solo suicide, but this ended
up being a lover's suicide, Araragi-senpai.
自殺のつもりが
心中になってしまいましたね 阿良々木先輩
Let me make it clear, but I'm
not a young girl, you know?
言っておきますけれど
私は幼女じゃないですよ?
That doesn't matter. Even then, you're like a
newborn baby, born merely six month ago, right?
構わない... それでも... 生後半年の...
生まれたての赤子... みたいなものだろ
Babies should be protected like this.
If you're saying what I have been
doing until now wasn't wrong...
これまで僕がしてきたことが間違いじゃなかったと言うのなら
...the fact that I'm doing this right now
should not be wrong, either.
今 こうしていることも
きっと間違いじゃないはずだ
I am not wrong.
僕は 間違えてない
Yup.
そう
Just as you are not wrong.
きみが間違えていないように
Really...
まったく...
You are foolish.
愚かですねえ
Not quite.
そうでもないさ
I can't make fun of you...
馬鹿にできない
...as you finally fight for your own sake.
やっと 自分のために戦ったんだね
I respect you, Araragi-kun.
僕はきみを尊敬するよ 阿良々木くん
I win.
私の... 勝ち
This a joke.
嘘みたい
Hanekawa-senpai really brought him here...
all the way from Antarctica.
羽川先輩 本当に連れて来たんだ
南極大陸から
She's really insane.
頭おかしいよ あの人
Hitagi, if this is the case, it wasn't,
"This is a pen." It was "dépaysement."
Come to think of it, Ougi-chan had been
alarmed at Hanekawa from the beginning.
The name "Ougi"...
actually was "ougi" because you put
a "door" on "wings (hane)," wasn't it?
Araragi-kun...
阿良々木くん
You oh-so-violently pushed my cute little
niece down. What are you planning to do?
僕の可愛い姪っ子を乱暴に押し倒して
何をするつもりだよ
Really, Araragi-kun, you're
so full of spirit.
まったく 阿良々木くんは元気いいなあ
Did something nice happen
to you or something?
何かいいことでもあったのかい?
You shouldn't be doing obscene things to your
underclassman when you have a lover.
恋人のいる身で
学校の後輩にいかがわしいことをするもんじゃないよ
Niece?
That's what he said.
In reference to Ougi-chan.
Meme Oshino said so.
Meme Oshino acknowledged
Ougi Oshino as a relative.
親戚として 忍野メメが忍野扇を認知したのである
What that signifies... is the
existence of Ougi Oshino.
それが何を意味するかと言えば
忍野扇の実在である
She was no longer a fabrication or a lie.
ここにいる彼女が
嘘偽りじゃあなくなった
That is why...
...the "darkness" disappeared.
You helped us, Oshino.
助かったよ... 忍野
I didn't really help or anything.
別に助けてないよ
You just helped yourself out
on your own, Araragi-kun.
きみが一人で勝手に助かっただけさ
阿良々木くん
Well done.
よくやった
Gweh...
ぐえ
Ougi Oshino became Ougi Oshino.
忍野扇は 忍野扇となった
And thus, the adolescence of me,
Koyomi Araragi, came to an end.
こうして僕 阿良々木暦の青春は終わった
I had believed that not taking care of
myself was the act of loving others.
自分を大切にしないことが他人を愛することだと信じていた
The days of kind deception, filled with thin,
weak euphoria, have now come to an end.
薄くて弱い陶酔に溢れた
優しい欺瞞の時代は終わりを迎えた
An epilogue.
後日談
March 15th
Big Brother! It's morning, damn it!
兄ちゃん朝だぞ こら!
If you don't get up, you'll be late!
起きなよ! 遅刻しちゃうよ
Jeez!
もう!
By the way, Tsukihi-chan,
what were you wishing for?
そう言えば月火ちゃん
お前の願掛けって一体なんだったの?
I mean, about your hair.
その髪についてなんだけれど
I was actually wishing your exams would go well,
and also a bit about Nadeko-chan.
実はお兄ちゃんの大学受験と
撫子ちゃんの件を お願いしてたんだよね
As it was about my hair (kami), I was
wishing upon the Lord God (kami).
髪のことだけに 神様に
That is, if he exists.
いたらだけれど
In any case, Big Brother's entrance exams are
over, and Nadeko-chan has gotten better for now.
お兄ちゃんの受験はともあれ終わったし
撫子ちゃんも 今んところ元気になったしね
Mm, maybe there is a God out there.
ふむ 神様はいるのかもしれない
Yeah, starting yesterday.
ああ 昨日からな
Hmm?
Oh, nothing.
いや なんでもない
I see.
あっそう
Big Brother, Big Brother! Since I'm going
to be in high school starting next month,
兄ちゃん兄ちゃん
あたしももう来月からは高校生だからさ
we won't be able to make
out like we have been.
今までみたいにいちゃいちゃできなくなるから
So let's take one last meal,
feeding mouth-to-mouth!
最後に口移しで食事しようぜ!
And let's brush each others' teeth!
そしてお互い 歯を磨き合おうぜ!
What you need to brush
up is your intelligence.
お前が磨くべきは知性だ
Well, you know, Karen-chan.
えっと なあ 火憐ちゃん
Even after you disband the Fire Sisters
of Tsuganoki 2nd Middle School,
お前 栂の木二中のファイヤーシスターズ解散後も
are you going to continue acting
as an advocate of justice?
正義の味方としての活動を続けるつもりなのか?
I can't help it!
是非もなし!
To correct, maybe she wanted
to say, "By all possible means!"
To be right, that is.
Karen-chan, in your case, what did
the "right thing" turn out to be?
火憐ちゃん お前にとって
正しさって 結局なんだった?
Helping others!
人助け!
I see.
そっか
Then why not start by helping yourself?
じゃ まずは自助努力から始めてみろ
You too.
Hey, Hachikuji!
よう 八九寺
Please don't speak to me!
話しかけないでください
Name: God
Mayoi Hachikuji
I am a god now!
わたし もう神様ですから
If you insist that you wish to speak to me,
after two bows, two claps, and one bow...
どうしても話しかけたいと言うのであれば
二礼二拍手一礼(にれいにはくしゅいちれい)したのちにお賽銭を渡し
One bow               Two claps                 Two bows
Manners in visitation
...make a monetary offering, and speak
as if you were speaking to a god.
ちゃんと神を遇するように話しかけてください
Who would talk to someone like that?
I'll totally ignore you.
誰がそんな奴に話しかけるんだよ
こっちからシカトだよ
Araragi-san, are you heading to
your graduation ceremony today?
阿良々木さんは今日 卒業式ですか?
Thank you for all your hard work.
お勤め ご苦労様でした
Normally, I would attend the graduation
ceremony and celebrate your achievement.
本来ならば卒業式に出席してお祝いして差し上げたいところなのですが
But if a god were to attend, the common people
might start clamoring... so I'll be considerate.
まあ神が行くと凡俗を騒がせてしまうかもしれませんから
気を遣っておきますね
Nobody will visit your shrine. We're going
to end up as a town without a god again!
お前の神社誰も参拝しないよ
また神不在の町になっちゃうよ
Hahaha! Oh, don't say that.
You can come by any time.
はっはっは まあそんなことを言わず
いつでもいらしてください
North Shirahebi Shrine is free to visit,
so really, come visit at any time.
北白蛇神社は自由参拝ですので
本当にいつでも遊びにきてください
Yeah, I'll go visit at any time.
ああ いつでも遊びに行くよ
At your home.
お前の家に
Yes, at my home!
はい わたしの家に
By the way, are you really all
right with this, Shinobu-san?
本当にいいのかい? 忍さん
Your desire to be sealed away once
again within Koyomin's shadow
こよみんの影に再び封じられたいというきみの望みは
is something I find difficult to comprehend.
理解しにくいものでもある
If there's some rationale behind
this, I'd like to know it.
何か考えがあるのなら
ここで明かしておいて欲しいものだ
There is none.
考えなどない
Besides, my desire to once again be
deemed harmless, as I tire of battle...
それに戦いに飽いた儂が
再び無害認定を受けられる立場になりたいと望むことは
is something a specialist shouldn't
find too difficult to comprehend.
専門家的には
そう理解しがたいことでもあるまい?
From a young girl (youjo)
to a phantom woman (youjo).
And then, to wish to return
to a young girl once again.
Of course, if my master, now that his vampiric
nature has been successfully removed,
かかっ むろん
吸血鬼成分を完全に取り除くことに成功した我があるじ様が
is unwilling to return once again to the
state of being a quasi-human, quasi-vampire,
人間もどきの吸血鬼もどきという曖昧な存在に
再び戻ることを嫌がると言うのならば
I shall retract my own desires.
儂は自分の願いを引っ込めるがの
After I heal that arm, I will retreat to a
mountain somewhere, and live a secluded life.
その腕を治したのち どこかの山にでも引っ込んで
隠棲するわい
Like I'd let you.
させるかよ
The mountains don't have any
Mister Donut stores, Shinobu.
山ん中にミスタードーナツの支店はないぜ 忍
Oh, that's right.
そうじゃったの
If you were to die tomorrow, I'd be fine with
tomorrow being the last day of my life.
お前が明日死ぬのなら
僕の命は明日まででいい
If you were to live through today,
I will also choose to live through today.
お前が今日を生きてくれるなら
僕もまた 今日を生きていこう
If you were to die the day after tomorrow,
I shall live for three days' time...
お前様が明後日死ぬのなら
儂は明々後日まで生きて
and tell a tale about you to someone.
誰かに お前様の話をしよう
I shall recite the story of my master
with pride to a listening ear.
我があるじ様の話を誇らしく
語って聞かせよう
Graduation Ceremony
Naoetsu High
Morning, Araragi-kun.
おはよう 阿良々木くん
Morning, Hanekawa.
おはよう 羽川
Why are you here at the bicycle lot?
どうして自転車置き場に?
Of course, I was waiting
for you, Araragi-kun.
もちろん 阿良々木くんを待ってたんだよ
Because there were a lot of things
I wanted to talk to you about.
色々 話しておきたいことがあったから
I have to take off right after
the graduation ceremony is over.
私 卒業式が終わったら
その足で出発しなきゃなんないから
So I thought this was the only
time I'd get to talk to you.
まあ 二人で話ができるタイミングって
ここくらいしかないかって
Do you have to leave right away
because of the flight you booked?
飛行機の予約の都合か?
すぐに出発しなきゃいけないっていうのは
Mm... Actually...
んん それはねー
In bringing Oshino-san back from Antarctica,
I sold off a bit of my brains.
忍野さんを南極から連れて帰ってくるにあたって
ちょっと頭脳を売ったから
Sold off your brains?
頭脳を売った?
What? That doesn't sound good...
何それ
不穏当な響きだけど
I guess you call them "jet setters"?
ジェットセッターって奴?
Well, I had to go that far
to charter a fighter plane.
まあそれくらいしないと
戦闘機はチャーターできなかったからね
It's fine. I sold it off to a
relatively honest institution.
大丈夫
比較的良心的な機関に販売したから
Stare
I'll knock you out!
張っ倒すよ
Scary!
こわっ
Graduation Ceremony Site
By the way, they think that Kagenui-san
is probably at the North Pole.
そう言えば...
影縫さんは北極にいるらしいことが判明したぜ
Graduation Ceremony Site
Graduation Ceremony
I see... I had a hunch
so I chose the continent.
そっか なんとなくの勘で大陸側を選んだんだけれど
Graduation Ceremony Site
Graduation Ceremony
So even if I had gone to the North
Pole, it still would've worked out.
じゃあたとえ北極を選んでいたとしても
別に外れではなかったんだね
Graduation Ceremony
Graduation Ceremony Site
斧乃木ちゃんが迎えに行こうとしたんだけれど
Ononoki-chan wanted to go get her, but she declined,
今 ホッキョクグマと戦うという
どこかで聞いたような武者修行に興じているから
saying she's busy with some kind of
familiar sounding training ritual
which involves fighting polar bears.
いいって言ってるらしい
Oh? Then, what happened to Ononoki-chan?
What is she doing now?
え じゃあ斧乃木ちゃんは?
今 どうしてるの?
Graduation Ceremony Site
She's still at my house.
まだ僕の家にいる
That's...
それは...
Well, a part of it is that Gaen-san
and Oshino left all too suddenly.
まあ 臥煙さんや忍野のほうが
急出発過ぎるっていうのもあるんだけどな
Graduation Ceremony
It looks like adults are
pretty busy in many ways.
色々忙しいみたいだぜ 大人は
Adults?
大人って...
Graduation Ceremony
But we're going to join
them starting tomorrow.
明日から私達もそうなるんでしょ?
Hitagi and I are still students.
僕やひたぎはまだ学生だよ
Graduation Ceremony
You're the only one that
is becoming an adult.
大人になるのはお前だけだ
"Hitagi"?
ひたぎ?
Oh, I see, I see. Something like
that happened while I was gone?
へー そうなんだ そうなんだ
私がいない間にそんなことが
Graduation Ceremony
Wait, wait, wait. Don't make hasty decisions.
待て待て待て 判断を慌てるな
Perhaps things haven't gone
as far as you think they have.
もしかするとお前が思っているほどのことは起きていないかもしれないぞ
I'm glad, I'm glad. Now, I can take off
without worrying about a thing.
よかったよかった
これで心置きなく 出発できるや
Morning, Araragi-kun.
おはよう 阿良々木くん
Oh? You're not going to call him "Koyomi"?
え? 暦って呼ばないの?
Morning, Koyomi.
おはよう暦
And welcome back, Tsubasa.
そしてお帰りなさい 翼
I'm back, Hitagi-chan.
ただいま ひたぎちゃん
Thursday, March 15th
Koyomi, Kanbaru apparently has prepared
a present for us as a graduation gift.
暦 神原が私達に卒業祝いにプレゼントを用意してくれているそうよ
Really? A present from Kanbaru...
That makes me nervous.
そうなのか? 神原からのプレゼント...
不安を煽られるな
Well, she isn't one to prepare something
strange for something like this.
いえ さすがにここで変なものを用意してくるあの子じゃあないわ
I probed a bit, and it seems to
be an ordinary flower bouquet.
探りを入れてみたところ
普通に花束みたい
Flowers, huh...
花ねえ
Off you go!
行ってらっしゃい
Yeah.
Pick up my diploma for me!
卒業証書は
代わりに受け取っといてくれ
I'm on my way.
You haven't changed, Araragi-senpai.
変わりませんねえ 阿良々木先輩
No, I'm changing.
いいや 変わるさ
But no matter how much I change...
だけどどんなに変わろうと
I am still me.
僕は僕のままなんだ
Graduation
Ceremony
Once upon a time, in a certain place,
there was a weirdo called Koyomi Araragi.
昔々あるところに
阿良々木暦という変な奴がおったそうじゃ
And he still is around to this day.
そしてそやつは 今もおる
And they all lived happily ever after.
めでたしめでたし
I heard the story recited from
the shadow that was running with me.
共に走る影から
そんな朗読が聞こえた
I was curious to see
what happened next in the story.
続きが気になる物語だった
Owarimonogatari
The End